Guide to the Stanford University Video Collection SC1031
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
- Videos
  - Luis Fraga tribute night, 2007 May 4; V330; 1 optical disc(s) (dvd)
    Fraga, Luis
  - Stanford in France VII video souvenirs, 2002, 2006; V331; 6 optical disc(s) (dvd)
    Overseas Studies
  - Paul V. Turner. "Stanford's Damaged Treasure: Frank Lloyd Wright's Hanna House" Stanford Channel, QuadrAngles Series, 1996; V332; 1 optical disc(s) (dvd)
    Turner, Paul V.; Hanna House
  - A World of Change; the International Initiative at Stanford University, 2005; V333; 1 optical disc(s) (dvd)
    Hennessy, John L.; Blacker, Coit D.; International relations Study and Teaching; Matson, P. A. (Pamela A.); Pate-Cornell, M. Elisabeth
  - Gerald Gunther Memorial Service, 2002 Oct 4; V334; 1 videotape(s) (vhs)
    Gunther, Gerald
  - Ernesto Galarza Lecture (Vilma Martinez) [Lessons from MALDEF; new strategies for old struggles], Apr 24, 1998; V335; 1 videotape(s) (betacam)
    Martinez, Vilma
  - Our Darling Boy; directed by Mike Attie and Melanie Levy, 2009; V336; 1 optical disc(s) (dvd)
  - Think Again source tapes, V337
  - Reflections, 1988 Aug 11; V338; 1 videotape(s) (vhs)
    Marine Biological Laboratory centennial special event with Katsuma Dan and Daniel Mazia in honor of their contributions to science and humanity. Welcome and introduction by Harlyn Halvorson and Shinya Inoue.
    Mazia, Daniel; Dan, Katsuma; Marine biology.
  - Institute for International Studies: Stanford as a World University, 1992; V339; 3 videotape(s) (vhs)
  - Stanford at the Crossroads: Planning for the Future, 1991; V340; 2 videotape(s) (vhs)
    Fund raising.; Hume, George; Kennedy, David M.
  - Information Explosion: The Political Power of Global Information, 1991; V341; 1 videotape(s) (vhs)
  - Organizational vision and visionary organizations / James Collins, 1991; V342; 1 videotape(s) (vhs)
    Collins, James C.
  - Stanford - A Place in History, V343; 1 videotape(s) (vhs)
  - Stanford "Stanford Observer" work in progress, V344; 1 videotape(s) (vhs)
  - Stanford University Freshman Perspective, 1994; V345; 1 videotape(s) (vhs)
  - Times to Remember: Voices of Stanford Law, V346; 1 videotape(s) (vhs)
  - Stanford Basketball "Reaching New Heights", 1991-1992; V347; 1 videotape(s) (vhs)
  - Earthquake Rebuilding., 1990; V348; 1 videotape(s) (vhs)
  - Excerpt from Gorbachev's visit to Stanford: Memorial Auditorium Address, V349; 1 videotape(s) (vhs)
  - Stanford Center for Innovations in Learning. Year in Review 2002-2003, V350; 1 optical disc(s) (dvd)
  - Los Munequitos de Matanzas / The Lively Arts at Stanford., 1992 Oct 11-12; V372; 2 videotape(s) (u-matic)
    First performance taped at Frost Amphitheater on Oct. 11, 1992; second performance taped at White Plaza on Oct. 12, 1992.
  - The Arms race, sources and solutions, 1981 May 28; V373; 3 videotape(s) (u-matic)
    Wolfgang Panofsky, Director of SLAC, Jeremy Stone, Director, Federation of Atomic Scientists, and Tony Webb, anti-nuclear activist, share their views on issues such as rates of technical advances in the arms race, political and psychological perceptions of adversaries' nuclear capabilities, negative byproducts of the arms race, and recurring questions concerning non-proliferation policies, society's willigness to continue financing or otherwise support the arms race, and the incipient creation of nuclear-free zones. A question-and-answer period follows. Panel discussion presented by Stanford Arms Control and Disarmament Forum at Stanford University on May 28, 1981. Moderated by Phil Farley, former Deputy Director, Arms Control Disarmament Agency.
  - Euromissiles: a panel discussion, 1983 Nov 16; V374; 2 videotape(s) (u-matic)
    Stephen Band of the British Embassy, and John P. Holdren, Professor of Energy and Resources, Berkeley, debate opposing views concerning the installation of Pershing IIs and Cruise missiles in Europe, the anticipated upsetting of the arms balance, the reduced possibility of arms control and the increased possibility of splitting NATO. Fellow panelist Hilmar Linnenkamp of the West German Defense Ministry and the Institute for East-West Security Studies points out the dramatic changes that have occured in Europe over the last 15 years and predicts that the most decisive factor in the debate will not be numbers of missiles nor nuclear strategies but the political "blood pressure" of Europe and the world. A question-and-answer period follows. Held at Stanford University, November 16, 1983 as part of the Forum on Intermediate Nuclear Forces: Pershing II and Cruise Missiles. Moderated by Coit Blacker of the Center for International Security and Arms Control.
  - Tribute to Peter Bing, 1994; V381; 5 videotape(s)
    "Tribute to Peter Bing" created by Stanford Health Care Education, Stanford University Hospital.
    Peter Bing, a member of the Stanford class of 1955, is an active supporter of Stanford University. He served on the Board of Trustees from 1970 to 1981, and 1986 to the present; was a member of the Haas Public Service Center Advisory Committee; and was one of four co-chairs of the Centennial Campaign. Peter Bing received the Stanford Associates' Degree of Uncommon Man Award in 1994.
  - The Uncommon Man: Dinner in Honor of Mr. Peter Bing, 1994; V382; 1 videotape(s) (vhs)
    In 1953 the Board of Governors created the degree of Uncommon Man/Uncommon Woman to honor those men and women who have rendered unique and outstanding service to the University. The degree was inspired by a statement made by Herbert Hoover, which said in part: "We believe in equal opportunity for all but we know that this includes the opportunity to rise to leadership in other words, to be uncommon." The degree is not given annually, nor at regularly prescribed intervals, but only when it is truly appropriate to honor someone for rare and extraordinary service to the University.
    Footage of the dinner honoring Peter Bing, recipient of the Stanford Associates' Degree of Uncommon Man Award in 1994.
  - Winds of Freedom, 2003; V383; 1 videotape(s) (vhs)
    This documentary covers the history of the Hoover Institution, its relationship with Stanford University, as well as past and current debates concerning the Institution's role on campus. Produced by documentary filmmaker Ian Slattery.
    The Hoover Institution on War, Revolution and Peace is a public policy think tank and library founded in 1919 by then future U.S. president, Herbert Hoover, an early alumnus of Stanford. The Hoover Institution is a unit of Stanford University, and is located on the campus. The Institution houses a large archive related to President Hoover, World War I, and World War II. Its mission statement outlines its basic tenets: representative government, private enterprise, peace, personal freedom, and the safeguards of the American system.
  - Chicano poet Raul Salinas, 1994; V0385; 3 videotape(s) (VHS)
    Chicano poet Raul Salinas/introduction & interview by Ben Olguin.
    Mexican American poets -- Interviews.; Genero, Jack.; Salinas, Raúl; Olguin, Ben.
  - The Stanford Presidency, 2005; V387; 1 optical disc(s) (dvd)
    Conversations with Richard Lyman, Donald Kennedy, Gerhard Casper, and John Hennessy, past and current presidents of Stanford University.
    Stanford University -- Presidents.; Casper, Gerhard; Kennedy, Donald; Hennessy, John; Lyman, Richard W.
  - William Bennett [US Sec. of Ed] speaking at Stanford, 1988 Apr; V394; 1 videotape(s) (vhs)
    Bennett, William
  - Stanford in Washington, V0398; 1 videotape(s) (vhs)
  - Large Gifts Fundraising Workshop with Bill Dailey, 1993; 1 videotape(s) (vhs)
  - Interview with Ambrosio Fornet, 1993; V400; 1 videotape(s) (vhs)
    Fornet is a Cuban literary and cinema critic, and also a scriptwriter. Here he talks about Cuban filmmaker Tomás Gutiérrez Alea's career.
    Motion picture producers and directors -- Cuba.; Motion pictures -- Cuba -- History.; Gutiérrez Alea, Tomás; Fornet, Ambrosio
  - Library Leadership: Confronting A Tumultuous Future, 1999 Sep 15; V402; 0 videotape(s) (vhs)
  - Stanford News: Stanford Library Repair, 1998 Apr 30; V403; 0 videotape(s) (vhs)
  - Stanford Builds For the 21st Century: Reconstruction, Restoration, and Renewal, V404; 0 videotape(s) (vhs)
  - The Stanford and Silicon Valley Project, 1996 Mar 01; V405; 0 videotape(s) (vhs)
  - Shakespeare on the Web: A Collaboration Experiment in Creative Education, 1996; V406; 0 videotape(s) (vhs)
  - Carmen Lomas Garza - Papel Picado Workshop, 1995 Feb 09; V407; 0 videotape(s) (hi-8)
  - Pechuca Film Lecture by Genero, 1994 Apr 19; V408; 0 videotape(s) (hi-8)
  - Palo Alto Weekly Centennial Symposium: The Communications Revolution; Where Are We Headed?, 1994 Oct 1; V409; 1 videotape(s) (vhs)
    Information technology -- History -- 20th century.; Technology -- social aspects.; Gunn, Moira; Lam, David; Giles, Peter; Grove, Andrew S.; Weiser, Mark; Saffo, Paul
  - How the Stanford network works: a short course in computer networking / Academic Information Resources, 1989; V410.1-2; 2 videotape(s) (vhs)
    Philip Almquist, senior systems programmer at Stanford University Network introduces beginners to elementary computer networking in the first tape (80 min.). He includes the basics of TCP/IP, the design of the Stanford network, and sources for further study. The second tape (100 min.) builds on the first, discussing TCP/IP more in depth and topics relevant to host and local network administrators. Also presents an advanced discussion of the design of the Stanford network and looks at its future.
  - Multimedia 201: beyond the basics / presented by Apple Computer's Higher Education Department; producer/director/writer, Dean Whitlow., 1991; V411; 1 videotape(s) (vhs)
    The program looks behind the technology at funding and support for multimedia technology. Shows some of the major successes in higher education - what they are doing and how they got it done.
  - Educom highlights: Educom 1992, 1993; V412; 1 videotape(s) (vhs)
    Highlights from Educom 1992 on the ways in which information technology is changing the future of higher education.
  - Multimedia in language and literacy / presented by Apple Computer's Education Group; producer, Robin Garthwait; director, Dean Whitlow, 1992; V413; 1 videotape(s) (vhs)
    Focuses on the different stages of communication: speaking, listening, writing, reading, and the integral role technology plays. Explores how technology is a catalyst in the language and literacy process and how multimedia facilitates most learning styles.
  - Female gangs / Elizabeth Ayala, 1994; V414; 1 videotape(s) (vhs)
    Title from cassette label. Video taped presentation from Fernando Soriano's class, ChSt 107, Gangs and violence: application to Chicanos.
  - Gang heterogeneity / Martín Sánchez Jankowski, 1994; V415; 1 videotape(s) (vhs)
    Title from cassette label. Video taped presentation from Fernando Soriano's class, CHSt 107, Gangs and violence: application to Chicanos.
  - Exploring Internet Teleconference / Dynix, 1993 Dec 2; V416; 1 videotape(s) (vhs)
    Video teleconference designed for librarians, college and university teachers, and information specialists to introduce the Internet and show how it is used to improve information access.
  - Managing and using PC memory - Data-Tech Institute, 1992; V417; 1 videotape(s) (vhs)
    Explains what the different kinds of memory are, where they come from, and what they can and can't do. Shows what's involved with memory upgrades. Discusses memory manager software products in general: what they do, and how they work, with special emphasis on DOS 5.0's memory manager product. Looks at the power of OS/2 2.0
  - With our very own names: celebrating and empowering the voices of a diverse community / Carmen Tafolla, 1995; V418; 1 videotape(s) (vhs)
    Dr. Tafolla performs a series of brief monologues, portraying a variety of Mexican American characters and focusing on diversity in America.
  - Lexis/Nexis: a rhyme and a reason / Carey Heckman, Nancy Green, 1994 Feb 4; V419; 1 videotape(s) (vhs)
    Tutorial on searching the Lexis/Nexis databases.
  - Pedagogical overview / Stephen Ehrmann, 1993 Jan 15; V420; 1 videotape(s) (vhs)
    Overview on educational uses of information technologies.
  - Kron TV Archival - Hos II, 1999 Aug 24; V421.1-2; 2 videotape(s) (betacam-sp)
    pt. 1: 1967 - MLK Speech; Old Union Sit-in; 1970 anti-ROTC pt. 2: 1970 - Old Union; Pitzer resignation / search for a new president
  - Below the Skin Dance - Memorial Auditorium, 2003 Mar 1; V422; 1 videotape(s) (betacam-sp)
    Camera 1 Tape 1
  - Lucile Packard Children's Hospital - Open Heart Baby, 2002 Feb 21; V423; 1 videotape(s) (betacam-sp)
  - John Hutchinson Discovery - the Dinosaur and the Chicken, 2002 Mar 19; V424; 1 videotape(s) (betacam-sp)
  - Stanford College in Antarctica - George and Mary Lou Boone, 1986 Dec 27- 1987 Jan 12; V425; 1 videotape(s) (vhs)
  - Stanford Fleet Street Singers - Stanford Hymn Rap Video, 1988; V426; 1 videotape(s) (vhs)
    Filmed by Ken, Paul and Rebecca - performance by Fleet Street
  - Fleet Street Singers Spring Show - Kresger Auditorium, 1990 May 17; V427; 1 videotape(s) (vhs)
  - Stanford In Washington - Mary Lou and George Boone, V428; 1 videotape(s) (vhs)
  - Nicolás Buenaventura: Cuando el hombre es su palabra, 2001; V429; 1 videotape(s) (vhs)
    Storyteller Nicolás Buenaventura tells some of his stories and answers questions from the audience.
  - Graduation 1992 - Protection Master (Part 2), V430; 1 videotape(s) (vhs)
  - Cultural factors in behavior / Amado Padilla, 1994; V431; 1 videotape(s) (vhs)
    Amado Padilla discusses issues of cultural change with emphasis on socialization of culture and the way it plays out in people's behavior.
  - Historical presence of Chicanos in the Southwest / Carlos Vélez-Ibañez, 1994; V432; 1 videotape(s) (vhs)
    A presentation of the early history of the Chicano population in the Southwest.
  - Gangs, gender and family considerations / Joan Moore, 1994; V433; 1 videotape(s) (vhs)
    Joan moore discusses the issues of the role of family and gender in gangs and how they play a part in the differences between gangs and among gang members
  - An Interview with Mario Handler, 1994; V434; 1 videotape(s) (vhs)
    Mario Handler, a Latin American documentary filmmaker, discusses his life and his films.
  - The Stanford Digital Libraries Project, 1995; V435; 1 videotape(s) (vhs)
    Vicky Reich introduces the Digital Libraries Initiative. Terry Winograd presents the Stanford Digital Library Project from a computer scientist's view, covering distributed model (virtual library), designing the "glue" (Middleware), comprehensive models and interfaces, support for distributed sources and services, and automation-agents. Rebecca Lasher gives an overview of the computer science technical report project and summarizes the research on identifying electronic documents.
  - Taggers and gangs / Rod Hernandez, 1994; V436; 1 videotape(s) (vhs)
    Rod Hernandez makes a distinction between different types of graffiti artists, focusing on graffiti crew members and reviewing similarities they share with gang members.
  - Live and learn: an insider's guide to academic success in college / produced and directed by Britt L. Sjoerdsma for the Center for Teaching and Learning, Stanford University, 1989 Sept 19; V437; 1 videotape(s) (vhs)
    This dramatic presentation is designed to assist freshman in managing their busy schedules--effective use of time, setting priorities, developing reading and notetaking skills, etc.--in order to be successful in college.
  - S.F. Mission mural tour, 1997; V438; 1 videotape(s) (vhs)
    Muralist Ray Patlan gives a tour of the outdoor murals of San Francisco's Mission District.
  - Lecture by Alejandro Morales, 1993 May 27; V439; 1 videotape(s) (vhs)
    Recorded lecture for Spanish Seminar 389: Hiojosa & Morales (Stanford University. Dept. of Spanish and Portuguese), by Chicano writer Alejandro Morales, introduced by Luis Leal.
  - The 7th Annual Galarza Lecture: "Meztizaje: The formation of the chicano...", 1992 Apr 24; V440; 1 videotape(s) (vhs)
  - Stanford Undergraduate Scholars Program / video produced by Dan Woodard, 1990; V441; 1 videotape(s) (vhs)
    This program encourages students to spend a quarter or two with a black professor on exploring some subject of common interest.
  - Heritage: A series on the importance of Hispanic culture to contemporary America / producers, Joseph Tovares, Charles Vaughn; director, John Grossenbacher, 1989; V442; 1 videotape(s) (vhs)
  - Toward better schools: choice for the 90's / California State Assembly Committee on Education; produced by San Diego State University and KTVF Television, San Diego, 1989 Nov 16; V443; 1 videotape(s) (vhs)
    The proceedings of a forum held in San Diego, on choice for parents and students in the schools.
  - Bishop Desmond Tutu at Stanford, 1989; V444; 1 videotape(s) (vhs)
    Bishop Desmond Tutu speaks on apartheid at Stanford's Memorial Auditorium on the occasion of the first national Martin Luther King Day holiday. He emphasizes the necessity of the United States issuing economic sanctions against South Africa, saying that blacks are willing to suffer economically in order to receive the political rights they have been denied.
  - Lo antisublime posmoderno en "Atame" de Pedro Almodovar: conferencia / Gonzalo Navajas, 1991; V445; 1 videotape(s) (vhs)
    Prof. Navajas analyzes Pedro Almodóvar's film "Atame" through an aesthetic and postmodernist perspective.
  - Enajenación e ironia en los personajes de Arlt y Acosta: 5 de mayo de 1991; Alurista / Stanford University, Department of Spanish and Portuguese, V446; 1 videotape(s) (vhs)
  - Reconstructing the ethical canon in Chicana poetics: 10 de mayo de 1991 / Maria Herrera-Sobek, V447; 1 videotape(s) (vhs)
    Lecture on feminist poetics and the new ethical approach being offered by feminist authors with respect to social relations, sexual relations, and ethics in general.
  - Lecture by Carlos Monsiváis, 1991; V448; 1 videotape(s) (vhs)
    Lecture given by Carlos Monziváis concerning the practice of journalism in Mexico. He also speaks about the writing and interpretation of historical events.
  - Chicano cinema class & Zoot Suit week, 1990; V449; 1 videotape(s) (vhs)
    Talks by Luiz Valdez, Issac Artenstein, and Moctezuma Esparza on their films and about their experiences as Chicano filmmakers. Taped March 3, 8, and 15, 1990 at the third annual Zoot Suit Event at Stanford University, sponsored by Casa Zapata and the Chicano Cinema class in March 1990.
  - Silent no more, a Chicana's vision for leadership: the 6th Annual Ernesto Galarza lecture series/ by Polly Baca, 1991; V450; 1 videotape(s) (vhs)
    After introductions and the awarding of the Ernesto Galarza prizes, Polly Baca lectures on the role in American society of Chicanas and their potential for leadership
  - Indirect charges at Stanford University: hearing of the House Subcommittee on Oversight and Investigations, 1991 Mar 13; V451; 1 videotape(s) (vhs)
    Hearing before the Subcommittee on Oversight and Investigations on indirect cost recovery practices at Stanford University for federal research grants and contracts.
  - When the critical "they" are "us" / Juan Bruce-Novoa, 1991; V452; 1 videotape(s) (vhs)
    Lecture on the literary process in Chicano writing in which Prof. Bruce-Novoa examines Chicano literary works using internal contexts vs. external contexts.
  - Poéticas feministas a la Mexicana/Chicana: Norma Alarcón, 1991 May 21; V453; 1 videotape(s) (vhs)
    Lecture on the influences and origins of Chicana poets and feminist poetry.
  - John Beverley lecture, 1991 May 6; V454; 1 videotape(s) (vhs)
    Lecture by Hispanic literature specialist John Beverly to the Stanford University Dept. of Spanish and Portuguese on the topic of testimony, narrative truth, and Latin American post-modernity in I, Rigoberta Menchu.
  - Ideología e identidad en la narrativa Chicana: Stanford University, Department of Spanish and Portuguese; Lauro Flores, 1991; V455; 1 videotape(s) (vhs)
    Explores ideas of ideology and identity in Chicano literature.
  - New Mexico literature: a paradigm of reconstruction: Francisco Lomelí, 1991; V456; 1 videotape(s) (vhs)
    Lecture given by Francisco A. Lomelí focusing on the reconstruction of Hispanic literary heritage in New Mexico.
  - Ginsberg reading: San Francisco, 1982; V457; 1 videotape(s) (vhs)
    Allen Ginsberg and Gregory Corso reading poems at the Kibuki Theater, San Francisco, Calif., 1982
  - Jeanie Meerapfel - Interview, 1993 Dec; V458; 1 videotape(s) (vhs)
  - [Untitled], V459; 1 videotape(s) (betacam-sp)
  - NASA, V460; 1 videotape(s) (vhs)
  - Eine Eliteschmiede wird 100 Jahre alt: die Stanford Universitat zwischen forschung und Lehre, Wirtschaft und Politik / ein Film von Dieter Winnhuber; Redaktion, Helmut Engelhardt, 1985; V461; 1 videotape(s) (u-matic)
    Tape was filmed at Stanford in September/October 1985, on the occasion of the University's Centennial. With interviews of the administration, faculty and students (voiceovers in German), scenes of research, study and social activities, as well as views of the setting of Stanford and its impact on Silicon Valley, this film gives a broad spectrum of the University for a German audience.
  - Interview with Hilia Moreira, 1993; V462; 1 videotape(s) (vhs)
    Interviewer: Jorge Ruffinelli.
  - Memory, cultural identity, and the social imaginary: art of the Chicana/o community / Amalia Mesa-Bains., 1995; V463; 1 videotape(s) (vhs)
    Amalia Mesa-Bains presents a series of slides of works by Chicano artists as a counter part to the academic perspective on Chicano studies, demonstrating the role of the Chicano visual art in the development of critical consciousness and the artists' contributions in the construction of cultural identity.
  - Catherine Peck Stanford football footage [videorecording], V464; 1 optical disc(s) (dvd)
  - discover Stanford, undated; v465; 1 videotape(s) (vhs)
  - The September 11th/2001 Attacks in Historical Perspective, 2001-10-01; V466; 1 videotape(s) (vhs)
    September 11 Terrorist Attacks, 2001 -- Public opinion -- California -- Stanford.; Stanford University. Department of History.
  - Hopkins Marine, 1992-07-09; V467; 1 videotape(s) (u-matic)
    Hopkins Marine Station
  - "Bay Area Veterans of the Civil Rights Movement" event video footage, V468; 1 hard drive(s) (external)
    In April of 2015, Dr. Clayborne Carson, Professor of American History and Director of the Martin Luther King, Jr., Research and Education Institute at Stanford University joined civil rights veterans to share stories and insights from the Freedom Movement. Participants explored how fear and courage affected their social activism and personal life, as well as how family influenced and was impacted by, movement participation.
    Civil rights movements -- United States.; Carson, Clayborne, 1944-; Student Nonviolent Coordinating Committee (U.S.)
  - Introduction to CMS/XEDIT (Part I); Stanford Instructional Television Network/Stanford University. Academic Information Resources, 1988-9-7; V469; 1 videotape(s) (VHS)
    XEDIT; VM/CMS; Stanford University. Stanford Instructional Television Network
  - Introduction to CMS/XEDIT (Part II); Ray Peck; Stanford Instructional Television Network/Stanford University. Academic Information Resources., 1989-6-15; V470; 1 videotape(s) (VHS)
    This class covers introductory and intermediate commands for XEDIT, advanced mail commands, and other topics. It is intended for those who know the basics of VM/CMS and XEDIT and would like to learn additional commands to improve their skills. Course conducted by Ray Peck.